Preliminary Guide to the William Erwin Stauber papers, 1942-1980 and undated (bulk 1942-1945 )
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
William Erwin Stauber papers 1942-1980 and undated, bulk 1942-1945
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Stauber, William Erwin
2.4 Linear Feet 1800 Items
Head of a Durham, N.C. advertising firm and lieutenant in the U.S. Navy during WWII.
Collection contains materials related to Stauber's service in the U.S. Navy during World War II. Some of the material contains notes and scripts of announcements and news reports made by Stauber on a radio show onboard the USS Biloxi. These radio broadcasts are dated January-April and document, among other things, the US invasion of Iwo Jima and contain marks of official censorship. A large part of the collection consists of correspondence, primarily from Stauber to his mother (1942-1945). Also included are photographs of USS Biloxi reunions (1974-1980), one of which was located in Durham, North Carolina.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The William Erwin Stauber papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2007.
Biographical Note
William (Bill) Erwin Stauber ran an advertising agency in Durham, N.C. and was a Durham County Commissioner in the 1970s. Stauber graduated from the University of North Carolina in 1940 and became a production manager for WPTF Radio in Raleigh, N.C. Stauber enlisted in the U.S. Navy in 1942 and was a deck officer on the light cruiser USS Biloxi in a year and half tour in the Pacific. In 1945, the commanding officer of the Biloxi arranged for Stauber to make a daily 3:45 radio broadcast for the ship, giving the crew news from the communications office.
Collection Overview
Collection contains materials related to Stauber's service in the U.S. Navy during World War II. Some of the material contains notes and scripts of announcements and news reports made by Stauber on radio broadcasts onboard the USS Biloxi. These radio broadcasts are dated January-April, 1945 and document, among other things, the U.S. invasion of Iwo Jima and contain marks of official censorship. A large part of the collection consists of correspondence, primarily from Stauber to his mother (1942-1945). Also included are photographs of USS Biloxi reunions (1974-1980), one of which was located in Durham, North Carolina.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Stauber, William Erwin
Iwo Jima, Battle of, Japan, 1945
World War, 1939-1945 -- Personal narratives, American
World War, 1939-1945 -- Correspondence
United States.--Navy -- Sea life -- World War, 1939-1945
Photographs
Contents of Collection
- Accession, 2007 (2007-0131), 4 Boxes
  Collection contains materials related to Stauber's service in the U.S. Navy during World War II. Some of the material contains notes and scripts of announcements and news reports made by Stauber on a radio show onboard the USS Biloxi. These radio broadcasts are dated January-April 1945 and document, among other things, the U.S. invasion of Iwo Jima and contain marks of official censorship. A large part of the collection consists of correspondence, primarily from Stauber to his mother (1942-1945). Also included are photographs of USS Biloxi reunions (1974-1980), one of which was located in Durham, North Carolina.
  - Radio show notes (Box 1)
    Handwritten notes for radio broadcasts on the USS Biloxi. Dated January-April, 1945, these shows contain news and updates related to the Biloxi' service in the Pacific, most notably during the United States invasion of Iwo Jima.
    - January 1-January 6, 1945
    - January 7-January 11, 1945
    - January 12-January 19, 1945
    - January 20-January 25, 1945
    - February 10-February 18, 1945
    - February 19-February 28, 1945
    - March 21-March 31, 1945
    - April 1-April 10, 1945
  - Radio show notes (Box 2)
    - Typed script, August 27, 1944
  - Personal notes and clippings
  - Correspondence, January 21, 1942-May, 1943
    Primarily consists of letters from Stauber to his mother. The letters chronicle his training and service during the war.
  - Correspondence, June, 1943-October, 1944 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, November, 1944-November, 1945 (Box 4)
  - Photographs, 1974-1980 and undated
    - USS Biloxi reunions, 1974-1980
    - Photographs of a ship's mast
      Mast in a park. Presumably a memorial for the Biloxi.
- Accession (2012-0081), 1943-1980, (1 box)
  This series includes images from Stauber's military career and private life; records from his time in the military, including health information, roster of officers, etc.; newspaper clippings; correspondence and military orders; and records on the event of various reunions for the crew of the USS Biloxi. The reunion subseries contains a book with extensive photographs of the mariners, the USS Biloxi, and their travels.
  - Correspondence & Military Orders, 1940s (Box 1)
  - Correspondence & Military Orders, 1950s
  - Records
  - Reunion 1974
  - Newspapers & Publicity
  - Photographs